# Frédéric Menou

#### contact@frederic.menou.me

## What I do

I'm a software engineer with recents experiences in management and hiring for a start-up. I can help build a team from scratch, make architectural decisions, and create a product culture.

I can help you structure and expand your tech team, take over a MVP, and build a product team.

More on me and what I believe in at <a href="https://frederic.menou.me">https://frederic.menou.me</a>.

# **Positions**

June 2021 to July 2022

### Fretlink, France - Solutions Architect

- Technical leadership for the whole team (up to 17 developers in 2022)
- Head of the Devops team
- Technical adviser to the CPO for the roadmap

September 2016 to May 2021

### Fretlink, France - CTO

- Management and technical leadership for the whole team (up to 15 developers in 2021), hiring, 1-1s and yearly reviews. Reporting to CODIR.
- Technical adviser to the CPO for the roadmap.
- Head of the Devops team.
- Helped the company raise 6M€ in 2017 and 18M€ in 2020.

May 2015 to August 2016

## Capitaine Train, Paris, France - CTO

- Management and technical leadership for the whole team (up to 25 developers in 2016), hiring, 1-1s and yearly reviews. Reporting to CODIR.
- Technical adviser to the CPO for the roadmap.
- Head of the Devops team.
- Capitaine Train was acquired by Trainline for an undisclosed amount around 140M€ in 2016.

June 2012 to May 2015

## Capitaine Train, Paris, France - Software Engineer

- Integration of tier APIs (carriers inventories and booking systems)
- Development and maintenance of booking and after sales backend
- Part-time Devops (scripting, CI, deployment procedures and tooling for developers)
- Hired 10 developers (it was a team effort)

October 2010 to June 2012

**Sfeir, Paris, France** – *Software Engineer as contractor* 

- Java GWT developer at BRED (Banque Populaire)
- Java Swing developer at KXEN (now a SAP company)
- Java developer at Embix (a Alstom startup)
- Java developer at Altergaz (a Eni startup)

September 2007 to September 2010

**StepInfo**, **Paris**, **France** - *Software Engineer as contractor* 

- Java developer at SGCIB, working on back-office for exotic derivatives products
- Technical support, release management, new features and issue investigation
- JavaEE components with a bit of Swing (UI) and JNI (integration of the pricing library written in C++)

# **Formation**

2002 - 2006

Ecole des Mines d'Alès, Alès, France-Diplôme d'ingénieur généraliste

Formation continue généraliste, spécialité informatique productique et réseau en dernière année.

154ème promotion

2006 - 2007

**Institut EERIE, Nîmes, France**- *Master 2* 

Spécialité informatique productique et réseau.

Stage de fin d'études en assistance à MOA à la SNCF, division immobilière. Mars à août 2007.

# A bit more about me

I've spent quite some time online or at conferences and tech meetups advocating for agile practices and using strongly typed functional programming languages such as Haskell, Purescript or Dhall.

You'll find more details and links to videos on those matters at <a href="https://frederic.menou.me">https://frederic.menou.me</a>.